nginx JS — Dynamic Reconfiguration Guide (servers)

│ DRAFT FOR COMMENTS — This document is a work in progress. Content, API names, and examples are subject to change before release.

Overview

This guide covers runtime management of nginx server blocks via the JavaScript DOM: adding, removing, renaming, and reconfiguring virtual servers, including their SSL configuration.

Prerequisites: read the for single worker guide first for write_mode, snapshot(), and suspendAcceptance(); and the locations guide for addLocation(), removeLocation(), and clone().

The two-phase commit model

Server-level structural operations (add, remove, rename) follow a two-phase model:

Phase 1 — Structural change:
nginx.http.addServer(name) ← server added to nginx.http.servers[]
nginx.http.removeServer(name) ← server removed from nginx.http.servers[]
srv.setNames([...]) ← server_name list updated in memory
After Phase 1: nginx.http.servers[] reflects the change, but the
server-name hash tables are NOT yet updated. Real HTTP requests
still route according to the OLD hash.
Phase 2 — Activate routing:
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch()
After Phase 2: the server-name hash is rebuilt from all current
nginx.http.servers[]. New requests are dispatched to the updated set.

This is intentional: it lets you prepare a server completely (add locations, set handler, configure SSL) before any request can reach it.

: addLocation() and removeLocation() (location-level changes) do not require a rebuildVhostDispatch() call — they update the location BST immediately.

What this guide covers

Topic │ API

Inspect servers │ nginx.http.servers[], srv.name, srv.names, srv.locations

Add server │ nginx.http.addServer(name [, opts]) + rebuildVhostDispatch()

Remove server │ nginx.http.removeServer(name) + rebuildVhostDispatch()

Clone server │ srv.clone(newName) + rebuildVhostDispatch()

Rename / multi-name │ srv.setNames([…]) + rebuildVhostDispatch()

Reconfigure properties │ srv.root, srv.clientHeaderTimeout, srv.mergeSlashes, etc.

SSL reconfiguration │ srv.ssl.setCertificate(), ssl.setProtocols(), ssl.setCiphers()

Test routing │ nginx.http.match(uri [, serverName])

Atomicity │ suspendAcceptance(), suspendAllWorkers()

Inspecting servers

nginx.http.servers[]

The live array of all NginxServer objects registered on the HTTP module. Includes both static (from nginx.conf) and dynamically added servers.

// List all servers and their names
nginx.http.servers.forEach((srv, i) => {
nginx.log(`servers[${i}]: ${srv.names.join(', ')} (${srv.locations.length} locations)`);
});

Server identity properties

Property │ Access │ Description

name │ read-only │ First server_name string, or "" if none.

names │ read-only │ Array of all server_name strings for this server.

root │ read/write │ Document root from the server’s implicit / location.

locations │ read-only │ Array of NginxLocation objects (see locations guide).

Finding a server by name

function findServer(name) {
return nginx.http.servers.find(srv =>
srv.names.some(n => n.toLowerCase() === name.toLowerCase())
) || null;
}
const api = findServer('api.example.com');
if (api) {
nginx.log('api root: ' + api.root);
}

nginx.http.match(uri [, serverName])

Simulates nginx’s location dispatch algorithm on the JavaScript side. Returns the NginxLocation that would handle uri, or null if no location matches.

// Test location dispatch on the first server
const loc = nginx.http.match('/api/v2/users');
nginx.log(loc ? 'matched: ' + loc.path : 'no match');
// Test on a specific virtual host
const loc2 = nginx.http.match('/static/img.png', 'cdn.example.com');

Useful for verifying that addLocation() / removeLocation() changes route requests as expected before enabling them for real traffic.

match('/api/v2/users', 'api.example.com'):
Scans prefix_locs[] → /api/v2/ (longest prefix match)
Checks regex_locs[] → no match
Returns: NginxLocation { path: '/api/v2/', matchType: 'prefix' }

Adding servers

nginx.http.addServer(name [, opts])

Creates a new virtual server with name as its primary server_name. The server is added to nginx.http.servers[] and to every listening address’s vhost dispatch table, but routing does not activate until rebuildVhostDispatch() is called.

const newSrv = nginx.http.addServer('new.example.com');
// … configure locations, handler, etc. …
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch(); // activate routing

Options:

Option │ Description

template: 'name' │ Use the named server as the configuration template (inherits server-level defaults such as clientHeaderTimeout, mergeSlashes, etc.). Defaults to the first server in nginx.http.servers[]. The new server starts with an empty location tree regardless of the template’s locations — use srv.clone() if you need to copy locations.

Difference between addServer and clone

│ nginx.http.addServer(name, {template}) │ srv.clone(newName)

Location tree │ Empty (no locations) │ Full copy of source locations

Config values │ Inherited from template │ Copied from source (shallow copy)

Location clcf sharing │ — (no locations yet) │ Shared initially; independent after addLocation()

Use case │ Build a new server from scratch │ Duplicate an existing server

Example: add a server and populate locations

// js_source: provision.js
const srv = nginx.http.addServer('tenant-acme.example.com');
// Document root
srv.root = '/var/www/tenants/acme';
// Health endpoint
const health = srv.addLocation('= /health');
health.handler = (req) => {
req.respond(200, {}, 'OK');
};
// Static files
const static_ = srv.addLocation('/static/');
static_.root = '/var/www/tenants/acme/static';
static_.sendfile = true;
// Activate routing
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();

Example: add server from template

// Inherit clientHeaderTimeout, mergeSlashes, etc. from 'base.example.com'
const newSrv = nginx.http.addServer('beta.example.com',
{ template: 'base.example.com' });
// Add locations specific to the beta server
const beta = newSrv.addLocation('/beta/');
beta.handler = betaHandler;
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();

Flow diagram: addServer two-phase

Phase 1: nginx.http.addServer('new.example.com')
─────────────────────────────────────────────────
nginx.http.servers[] vhost dispatch tables
────────────────── ────────────────────────
[0] example.com addr_conf->virtual_names
[1] api.example.com hash: example.com → [0]
[2] new.example.com ←NEW api.example.com → [1]
← hash NOT YET updated
← requests for new.example.com →
no match → fall back to default
Phase 2: nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch()
──────────────────────────────────────────
vhost dispatch tables rebuilt:
hash: example.com → [0]
api.example.com → [1]
new.example.com → [2] ← NOW ACTIVE

Removing servers

nginx.http.removeServer(name)

Removes the server whose primary name (case-insensitive) matches name. Splices it from nginx.http.servers[] and from every listening address’s vhost entry list. Returns true if found and removed, false otherwise.

Must call rebuildVhostDispatch() to stop routing requests to the removed server.

const removed = nginx.http.removeServer('old.example.com');
if (removed) {
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
}

: In-flight requests being processed by the removed server’s handlers complete normally. The server’s config memory is not freed until the server opaque object is garbage-collected.

Example: dynamic server lifecycle (add → serve → remove)

// Bring up a temporary server for a maintenance window
async function withTemporaryServer(name, handler, durationMs) {
const srv = nginx.http.addServer(name);
const loc = srv.addLocation('/');
loc.handler = handler;
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
nginx.log('temporary server live: ' + name);
await nginx.setTimeout(durationMs);
nginx.http.removeServer(name);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
nginx.log('temporary server removed: ' + name);
}
// Usage: maintenance page for 2 minutes
withTemporaryServer('maintenance.example.com',
(req) => { req.respond(503, {}, 'Maintenance in progress'); },
120000);

Flow diagram: removeServer two-phase

Before removeServer('api.example.com'):
servers[]: example.com, api.example.com, cdn.example.com
hash: all three names routable
Phase 1: nginx.http.removeServer('api.example.com')
servers[]: example.com, cdn.example.com
hash: still routes api.example.com → (now stale pointer)
← DANGER: do not leave this state for long
Phase 2: nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch()
hash rebuilt: example.com, cdn.example.com
Requests for api.example.com → no match → default server

Cloning a server

srv.clone(newName)

Creates an independent copy of the server under newName. Unlike addServer(), the clone inherits the full current location tree — all prefix, regex, and named locations (both static and dynamic).

const primary = findServer('example.com');
const mirror = primary.clone('mirror.example.com');
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();

Shared location structs after clone

After clone(), the source and clone initially share the underlying ngx_http_core_loc_conf_t C structs for each copied location. This means:

•

Reading loc.root / loc.handler / etc. on either server returns the same value.

•

Writing loc.handler = fn via a location object from either server modifies the shared struct and affects both servers.

•

Calling clone.addLocation('/new/') creates a new, independent entry only in the clone’s BST. It does not affect the source.

To make a location’s config truly independent after cloning, use loc.snapshot() on the clone’s location and then immediately restore() — this forces a copy-on-write. Or set the field you want to differ: the setter will write to the shared struct (which is still correct if you intend to update both), or use write_mode='local' for per-request isolation.

srv.clone('mirror.example.com'):
primary.locations: mirror.locations (after clone):
/api/ → clcf_A ─────────────► /api/ → clcf_A (shared pointer)
/static/ → clcf_B ─────────────► /static/ → clcf_B (shared pointer)
/ → clcf_C ─────────────► / → clcf_C (shared pointer)
mirror.addLocation('/mirror-only/'):
/mirror-only/ → clcf_NEW ← independent, only in mirror
primary.findLocation('/api/').handler = v2; ← modifies clcf_A
→ affects BOTH primary and mirror /api/

Example: blue-green deployment by server clone

// js_source: blue_green.js
let activeName = 'app.example.com';
let standbyName = 'app-standby.internal';
// Initial state: active server is live
const active = findServer(activeName);
async function deployGreen(newHandlers) {
// Clone active → standby (inherits all locations and settings)
const standby = active.clone(standbyName);
// Update handlers on standby
// (sets shared clcf, visible on both servers — that is fine here
// because standby is not yet routable)
newHandlers.forEach(({ path, handler }) => {
const loc = standby.findLocation(path);
if (loc) { loc.handler = handler; }
});
// Add standby to routing
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
nginx.log('standby live at: ' + standbyName);
// Smoke-test the standby via match() before cutover
const health = nginx.http.match('/health', standbyName);
nginx.log('standby health loc: ' + (health ? health.path : 'none'));
// Cutover: swap names
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
try {
active.setNames([standbyName]); // demote active to standby
standby.setNames([activeName]); // promote standby to active
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
} finally {
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
}
nginx.log('cutover complete: ' + activeName + ' → new handlers');
}

Managing server names

srv.setNames(namesArray)

Replaces the server_name list for this server. Strings are copied into the cycle pool. The change is visible immediately via srv.names and srv.name, but routing is not updated until rebuildVhostDispatch() is called.

const srv = findServer('example.com');
// Add an alias
srv.setNames(['example.com', 'www.example.com', 'example.net']);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();

// Remove all names (server becomes the default_server for its address)
srv.setNames([]);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();

: setNames replaces the entire name list. To add a single alias, read srv.names, push to it, and pass the updated array back.

function addAlias(srv, alias) {
const names = srv.names.slice(); // copy current names
if (!names.includes(alias)) {
names.push(alias);
srv.setNames(names);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
}
}
function removeAlias(srv, alias) {
const names = srv.names.filter(n => n !== alias);
srv.setNames(names);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
}

Example: certificate rollover with name swap

Wildcard certificates covering *.example.com can be rotated by swapping which server responds to each name:

async function swapServerNames(nameA, nameB) {
const srvA = findServer(nameA);
const srvB = findServer(nameB);
if (!srvA || !srvB) { throw new Error('server not found'); }
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
try {
const tempA = srvA.names.slice();
const tempB = srvB.names.slice();
srvA.setNames(tempB);
srvB.setNames(tempA);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
} finally {
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
}
}

Reconfiguring server properties

Writable server properties

Property │ Type │ Description

root │ string │ Document root for the implicit / location.

clientHeaderBufferSize │ number (bytes) │ Size of buffer for reading client request headers.

clientHeaderTimeout │ number (ms) │ Timeout for reading the full HTTP request header.

ignoreInvalidHeaders │ boolean │ Whether to ignore invalid header names (default: true).

mergeSlashes │ boolean │ Whether to merge consecutive slashes in URIs (default: true).

underscoresInHeaders │ boolean │ Whether to allow underscores in header names (default: false).

serverTokens │ 'on' | 'off' | 'build' │ Controls the Server: response header.

connectionPoolSize │ number (bytes) │ Size of the per-connection memory pool.

requestPoolSize │ number (bytes) │ Size of the per-request memory pool.

Read-only server properties

Property │ Description

largeClientHeaderBuffers │ Object with count and size (bytes). Set via nginx.conf only.

ssl │ NginxSSL sub-object, or null if SSL is not configured. SSL settings are mutated via ssl.setCertificate() etc.

Example: runtime header policy change

const srv = findServer('legacy.example.com');
// Legacy API clients send underscores in header names
nginx.suspendAcceptance();
srv.underscoresInHeaders = true;
srv.ignoreInvalidHeaders = false;
nginx.resumeAcceptance();

SSL reconfiguration

The NginxSSL sub-object

srv.ssl returns a NginxSSL wrapper if the server has ssl_certificate configured, or null otherwise.

const ssl = findServer('secure.example.com').ssl;
if (!ssl) { throw new Error('no SSL configured'); }

SSL read-only properties

Property │ Description

certificate │ Current certificate file path (string).

certificateKey │ Current private key file path (string).

protocols │ Array of enabled protocol strings (e.g. ['TLSv1.2', 'TLSv1.3']).

ciphers │ OpenSSL cipher string.

verify │ Client certificate verification mode ('off', 'on', 'optional', 'optional_no_ca').

clientCertificate │ Path to client CA bundle (or "" if not set).

trustedCertificate │ Path to trusted CA bundle (or "" if not set).

ecdhCurve │ ECDH curve name or "auto".

dhparam │ DH parameters file path (or "" if not set).

SSL read/write properties

Property │ Type │ Description

sessionTimeout │ number (seconds) │ TLS session cache timeout.

sessionTickets │ boolean │ Whether to use TLS session tickets.

preferServerCiphers │ boolean │ Whether to prefer the server’s cipher order.

verifyDepth │ number │ Maximum depth of client certificate chain.

ssl.setCertificate(certPath, keyPath)

Hot-swaps the TLS certificate and private key on the live SSL_CTX. Calls SSL_CTX_use_certificate_chain_file() and SSL_CTX_use_PrivateKey_file() (PEM format), then validates that the cert and key match.

Takes effect for all new TLS handshakes immediately. Existing sessions continue with the old certificate until they expire. Throws on any error (file not found, invalid format, key mismatch).

const ssl = findServer('secure.example.com').ssl;
ssl.setCertificate(
'/etc/ssl/certs/2025/secure.example.com.pem',
'/etc/ssl/private/2025/secure.example.com.key'
);
nginx.log('certificate rotated: ' + ssl.certificate);

ssl.setProtocols(protocolArray)

Sets the enabled TLS protocol versions on the live SSL_CTX.

Accepted values: 'SSLv2', 'SSLv3', 'TLSv1', 'TLSv1.1', 'TLSv1.2', 'TLSv1.3'.

// Enforce TLS 1.2+ only
ssl.setProtocols(['TLSv1.2', 'TLSv1.3']);
// Re-enable TLS 1.1 for legacy clients temporarily
ssl.setProtocols(['TLSv1.1', 'TLSv1.2', 'TLSv1.3']);

ssl.setCiphers(cipherString)

Sets the OpenSSL cipher suite string on the live SSL_CTX.

ssl.setCiphers('ECDHE-ECDSA-AES128-GCM-SHA256:ECDHE-RSA-AES128-GCM-SHA256');

Example: zero-downtime certificate rotation

loc.handler = async (req) => {
const body = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
const srvName = body.server;
const certPath = body.cert;
const keyPath = body.key;
const srv = findServer(srvName);
if (!srv) { req.respond(404, {}, 'server not found'); return; }
const ssl = srv.ssl;
if (!ssl) { req.respond(400, {}, 'server has no SSL'); return; }
const oldCert = ssl.certificate;
const oldKey = ssl.certificateKey;
try {
ssl.setCertificate(certPath, keyPath);
nginx.log(`cert rotated on ${srvName}: ${oldCert} → ${certPath}`);
req.json({ rotated: true, cert: ssl.certificate });
} catch (e) {
req.respond(500, {}, 'cert rotation failed: ' + e.message);
}
};

Example: emergency protocol downgrade

Allow older TLS versions temporarily for a critical client integration:

loc.handler = async (req) => {
const ssl = findServer('api.example.com').ssl;
const original = ssl.protocols.slice(); // save current protocols
// Allow TLS 1.1 for 10 minutes, then revert
ssl.setProtocols(['TLSv1.1', 'TLSv1.2', 'TLSv1.3']);
nginx.log('TLS 1.1 re-enabled temporarily');
await nginx.setTimeout(600000); // 10 min
ssl.setProtocols(original);
nginx.log('TLS protocols restored: ' + original.join(', '));
};

: ssl.protocols returns the current enabled protocol list. Saving and restoring it is equivalent to using snapshot() on a sub-object — an explicit save/restore is required here because NginxSSL does not currently support snapshot().

Complete examples

Example 1: per-tenant server provisioning

// js_source: tenants.js
const templateServer = nginx.http.servers[0];
function provisionTenant(tenant) {
const name = tenant.id + '.example.com';
// Idempotent: if already exists, return existing
const existing = findServer(name);
if (existing) { return existing; }
const srv = nginx.http.addServer(name);
srv.root = '/var/www/tenants/' + tenant.id;
// Standard locations
const health = srv.addLocation('= /health');
health.handler = (req) => { req.respond(200, {}, 'OK'); };
const api = srv.addLocation('/api/');
api.handler = makeTenantApiHandler(tenant);
const static_ = srv.addLocation('/static/');
static_.root = '/var/www/static';
static_.sendfile = true;
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
nginx.log('provisioned: ' + name);
return srv;
}
function deprovisionTenant(tenantId) {
const name = tenantId + '.example.com';
const removed = nginx.http.removeServer(name);
if (removed) {
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
nginx.log('deprovisioned: ' + name);
}
return removed;
}

Example 2: atomic blue-green server swap

let blueActive = true;
loc.handler = async (req) => {
const body = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
const flavor = body.flavor; // 'blue' or 'green'
const target = 'app.example.com';
// Build the new (inactive) server with the new handler
const newSrv = nginx.http.addServer(target + '-' + flavor);
const apiLoc = newSrv.addLocation('/api/');
apiLoc.handler = flavor === 'blue' ? blueHandler : greenHandler;
// Verify new server routes correctly via match() before cutover
const matched = nginx.http.match('/api/test', target + '-' + flavor);
if (!matched || !matched.handler) {
nginx.http.removeServer(target + '-' + flavor);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
req.respond(500, {}, 'route test failed');
return;
}
// Atomic cutover: suspend all workers, swap names, rebuild
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
try {
const oldSrv = findServer(target);
if (oldSrv) {
oldSrv.setNames([target + '-old']);
}
newSrv.setNames([target]);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
blueActive = (flavor === 'blue');
} finally {
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
}
// Clean up the old server after traffic drains
await nginx.setTimeout(30000);
nginx.http.removeServer(target + '-old');
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
req.json({ active: flavor });
};

Example 3: certificate rotation endpoint

// POST /admin/rotate-cert
// Body: { "server": "secure.example.com", "cert": "/path/cert.pem", "key": "/path/key.pem" }
loc.handler = async (req) => {
const body = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
const srv = findServer(body.server);
if (!srv || !srv.ssl) {
req.respond(404, {}, 'server or SSL not found');
return;
}
const ssl = srv.ssl;
const oldCert = ssl.certificate;
try {
ssl.setCertificate(body.cert, body.key);
req.json({
server: body.server,
old: oldCert,
new: ssl.certificate,
rotated: true,
});
} catch (e) {
req.respond(500, {}, e.message);
}
};

Example 4: server inventory endpoint

const inv = nginx.http.servers[0].addLocation('= /__servers');
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
inv.handler = (req) => {
const data = nginx.http.servers.map(srv => ({
name: srv.name,
names: srv.names,
root: srv.root,
locationCount: srv.locations.length,
hasSSL: srv.ssl !== null,
sslCert: srv.ssl ? srv.ssl.certificate : null,
sslProtocols: srv.ssl ? srv.ssl.protocols : null,
serverTokens: srv.serverTokens,
}));
req.json({ servers: data, count: data.length });
};

Example 5: validate routing before going live

Use nginx.http.match() to assert location dispatch is correct before calling rebuildVhostDispatch():

function validateRouting(srv) {
const cases = [
{ uri: '/health', expect: '= /health' },
{ uri: '/api/users', expect: '/api/' },
{ uri: '/static/a.js', expect: '/static/' },
{ uri: '/unknown/path', expect: '/' },
];
const errors = [];
cases.forEach(({ uri, expect }) => {
const loc = nginx.http.match(uri, srv.name);
if (!loc || loc.path !== expect) {
errors.push(`${uri}: expected '${expect}' got '${loc ? loc.path : 'null'}'`);
}
});
return errors;
}
// Usage before activating a new server:
const newSrv = nginx.http.addServer('new.example.com');
// … add locations …
const errors = validateRouting(newSrv);
if (errors.length > 0) {
nginx.http.removeServer('new.example.com');
throw new Error('Routing validation failed:\n' + errors.join('\n'));
}
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();

Atomicity and cross-worker propagation

Single-worker atomicity

Property writes on NginxServer and NginxSSL objects are individual assignments. Use suspendAcceptance() to make a multi-field update appear atomic to new requests on this worker:

nginx.suspendAcceptance();
srv.clientHeaderTimeout = 10000;
srv.underscoresInHeaders = true;
srv.ignoreInvalidHeaders = false;
nginx.resumeAcceptance();

Cross-worker atomicity

Server structural changes and rebuildVhostDispatch() affect only the current worker’s server-name hash. To propagate to all workers:

const cfgWorker = new SharedWorker('cfgworker.js');
// Each worker applies addServer fan-out from the SharedWorker:
cfgWorker.onmessage = (msg) => {
if (msg.data.op === 'addServer') {
const srv = nginx.http.addServer(msg.data.name, msg.data.opts);
// Re-apply locations/handlers from registry (functions can't be cloned)
msg.data.locationDefs.forEach(def => {
const loc = srv.addLocation(def.pattern);
if (def.root) { loc.root = def.root; }
if (def.handler) { loc.handler = handlerRegistry[def.handler]; }
});
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
} else if (msg.data.op === 'removeServer') {
nginx.http.removeServer(msg.data.name);
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
}
};

// Handler: add server across all workers atomically
loc.handler = async (req) => {
const cfg = JSON.parse(await req.readBody());
await nginx.suspendAllWorkers();
try {
// Apply locally
const srv = nginx.http.addServer(cfg.name, cfg.opts);
// … add locations …
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch();
// Broadcast to all other workers
cfgWorker.postMessage({
op: 'addServer',
name: cfg.name,
opts: cfg.opts,
locationDefs: cfg.locationDefs,
});
req.json({ added: cfg.name });
} finally {
await nginx.resumeAllWorkers();
}
};

Flow diagram: cross-worker addServer + rebuildVhostDispatch

Worker 0:
await suspendAllWorkers()
─────────────────────────────────────────► all workers suspended
nginx.http.addServer('new.example.com')
nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch() ← this worker's hash rebuilt
cfgWorker.postMessage({op:'addServer'})
│ ──────────────────────────────────► SharedWorker fan-out
│ ──────────────► Worker 1:
│ addServer()
│ rebuildVhostDispatch()
└ ──────────────► Worker 2:
addServer()
rebuildVhostDispatch()
await resumeAllWorkers()
─────────────────────────────────────────► all workers resume
All workers now route requests to new.example.com.

API Reference

nginx.http.servers[]

Read-only live array of all NginxServer objects.

NginxServer[] nginx.http.servers

nginx.http.addServer(name [, opts])

Creates a new virtual server with an empty location tree.

NginxServer nginx.http.addServer(name)
NginxServer nginx.http.addServer(name, { template: 'existingName' })

Does NOT activate routing — call rebuildVhostDispatch() after.

Throws TypeError if name is missing. Throws InternalError if no existing servers or no http{} block.

nginx.http.removeServer(name)

Removes the server matching name (case-insensitive).

boolean nginx.http.removeServer(name)

Returns true if removed, false if not found. Does NOT update routing — call rebuildVhostDispatch() after.

nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch()

Rebuilds the server-name hash tables for all listening addresses. Must be called after addServer(), removeServer(), or srv.setNames().

undefined nginx.http.rebuildVhostDispatch()

Throws InternalError on hash allocation or init failure.

nginx.http.match(uri [, serverName])

Simulates nginx’s location dispatch algorithm. Returns the NginxLocation that would handle uri, or null on no match.

NginxLocation | null nginx.http.match(uri)
NginxLocation | null nginx.http.match(uri, serverName)

Uses the first server in nginx.http.servers[] when serverName is omitted. Performs the full exact → prefix → ^~ → regex → fallback sequence on the JavaScript-side location arrays.

srv.clone(newName)

Creates an independent copy of the server (with full location tree).

NginxServer srv.clone(newName)

Does NOT activate routing — call rebuildVhostDispatch() after.

srv.setNames(namesArray)

Replaces the server_name list.

undefined srv.setNames([ 'name1', 'name2', ... ])

Does NOT update routing — call rebuildVhostDispatch() after.

Throws TypeError if the argument is not an array.

ssl.setCertificate(certPath, keyPath)

Hot-swaps the TLS certificate and private key on the live SSL_CTX.

undefined ssl.setCertificate(certPath, keyPath)

Takes effect for new handshakes immediately. Throws on file I/O error, PEM parse error, or cert/key mismatch.

ssl.setProtocols(protocolArray)

Sets enabled TLS protocol versions on the live SSL_CTX.

undefined ssl.setProtocols(['TLSv1.2', 'TLSv1.3'])

Accepted strings: 'SSLv2', 'SSLv3', 'TLSv1', 'TLSv1.1', 'TLSv1.2', 'TLSv1.3'.

ssl.setCiphers(cipherString)

Sets the OpenSSL cipher suite string.

undefined ssl.setCiphers(openSSLCipherString)

Design notes

Why rebuildVhostDispatch() is explicit

nginx’s server-name dispatch is based on hash tables built at startup. A single atomic rebuild — rather than incremental insertion — avoids hash collisions, wildcard ordering issues, and PCRE regex recompilation during partial updates. The explicit call gives the JS script control over exactly when the new routing becomes active.

addServer vs srv.clone: location tree sharing

nginx.http.addServer() always creates an empty location tree. This is deliberate: it forces the caller to explicitly define all locations for the new server, preventing unexpected inheritance of handler functions that may reference per-server state.

srv.clone() copies the full tree for cases where the intent is to create a near-identical virtual host. The initial struct sharing is safe because the clone is not yet reachable until rebuildVhostDispatch() is called, giving the caller a window to customise the clone before any request can reach it.

Certificate rotation and existing sessions

ssl.setCertificate() replaces the certificate on the live SSL_CTX using SSL_CTX_use_certificate_chain_file / SSL_CTX_use_PrivateKey_file. This is the standard OpenSSL hot-swap path. Sessions established before the swap continue with the old certificate via OpenSSL’s session cache or tickets; only new handshakes use the new certificate.

rebuildVhostDispatch and per-worker hashes

Each worker maintains its own server-name hash. A rebuildVhostDispatch() call on Worker 0 does not update Workers 1 … N. Broadcast via SharedWorker (see cross-worker section above) is required to synchronise all workers.

Duplicate server names

rebuildVhostDispatch() logs a warning (NGX_LOG_WARN) and skips duplicate server names silently — it does not throw. The first server registered with a given name wins. Ensure names are unique before calling addServer() if strict routing is required.